嘿，你们好，我是TheCherno，欢迎回到我的游戏引擎系列
hey, what's up guys, my name is TheCherno, welcome back to my game engine series
那么上期，我们看了顶点缓冲区布局，并且优雅地设计了一个处理所有那些东西的类
so last time we do a look at vertex buffer layouts, and we designed a class that could handle all of that stuff kind of for us and elegantly
因此它看起来很棒，一定要去看看那期视频哦，因为它确实包含了很多
so that it look nice, definitely make sure that you check out that video, because it's really informative
我想很多人也喜欢它，但它绝对不是，抱歉，因为我们接下来要讲的东西
I think a lot of people liked it as well, and it's definitely not, sorry, for kind of what we're moving on with next
也就是顶点数组，那就是我们今天这期视频要做的，顶点数组本质上是，在OpenGL中
which is gonna be talking about vertex arrays, and that's what we're gonna do in this video today, so vertex arrays are essentially, in OpenGL
它们被定义为，我的意思是，它们有点奇怪，老实说，我真的认为它应该存在
they're kind of defined as, I mean, they're a bit weird, to be honest, if I'm being completely honest with you, I really think that should exist
在OpenGL系列中确实做过，包含了顶点数组，看看吧，就像这个系列之前的视频一样
I do have a video, covering vertex arrays in the OpenGL series, check that out, again just like with the previous video in this series
我不想只解释很多过去已经解释过的，所以如果你们想了解更多细节，可以看看那期视频
I don't want to just explain a lot of stuff that I've already explained in the past, so check out that video, if you want more details
但本质上顶点数组是一种包含状态的实体，对吧，所以它们实际上不包含任何实际数据
but essentially vertex arrays are a kind of state containing entity, right, so what they don't actually contain any real data
就像顶点缓冲区，包含了顶点，索引缓冲区包含了索引
like your vertex buffer, is what contains your vertices, your index buffer is what contains the indeces
这两个缓冲区是你们的实际缓冲区，它们的内存缓冲区中有你们的实际数据
those 2 pieces of kind of like, those 2 buffers are your actual buffers, their memory buffers, they have your actual data
顶点数组实际上包含的只是对顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区的引用
what the vertex array actually contains is just references essentially to a vertex buffer and to an index buffer
还有一种叫做布局的东西，这当然是我们在上一期讨论过的
and also to something called a layout, which is of course what we talked about in the last episode
所以基本上就是你们创建了一个顶点数组，然后可以绑定一个顶点缓冲区到它上面
so basically what happens is you create a vertex array, and then you can bind a vertex buffer to it
顶点缓冲区和它的索引缓冲区，这两个东西，都在顶点数组中
and a vertex, I'm sorry and an index buffer to it, and those 2 kind of things, right, live inside that vertex array
现在需要注意的是，当我说它们生存在里面时，并不是说它们的字面副本存活在里面
now it's important to note that when I say they live inside it, it doesn't mean that like literal copies of them kind of live inside
并不是那种在里面的生存，我真正想说的是
it's not that kind of living inside, what I'm actually talking about is
顶点数组与这两个相关联与顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区相关联，但实际上不像
the vertex array is associated with those 2 kind of with the vertex buffer and the index buffer, but it's not actually like
它不能控制它的生存期，如果你们想修改顶点缓冲区本身
it doesn't control its lifetime, right, and you know, if you if you like modify the vertex buffer itself
它会修改顶点数组里的那个，因为顶点数组只有链接
it's going to modify the same one, that's inside the vertex array, because the vertex array just has links
那有点像指针，对吧，它们有指向现有顶点缓冲区和现有索引缓冲区的指针
that's kind like pointers, right, they just have pointers to an existing vertex buffer and to an existing index buffer
它们实际上不包含自己的，它们不拥有顶点缓冲区和索引缓冲区，只是引用它们，对吧
they don't actually contain their own, they don't own the vertex buffer and the index buffer, they just kind of reference them, right
然后它拥有的另一个东西本质上是VertexBuffer的所有布局信息
and then the other thing that it has is essentially all of the layout kind of information of our VertexBuffer
就像上期，我们讲了如何使用顶点属性指针
so just like in the last episode, we talked about how we had to use, like you know, vertex attribute pointers
我们设置了一个BufferLayout类和所有这些东西，那是朝向我说过的每个VertexBuffer
and we set up a BufferLayout class and all of that kind of stuff, right, that is toward kind of per VertexBuffer as I said
但是这个状态会存储在数组中，在VertexArray中，意味着，当重新绑定个VertexBuffer
but what happens is that state is stored in your array, in your VertexArray, which means that, when you rebind a VertexBuffer
你们不需要重新定义它的层，除非它被改变了，对吧，对于多个VertexBuffer来说有点不同
you don't need to redefine its layer, unless it's changed, right, and this works a little bit differently for multiple VertexBuffers
因为能做的是，你们实际上可以有一个VertexArray，然后有几个VertexBuffer
because what you can do is, you can actually have a VertexArray, and then have like several VertexBuffers
包含不同的信息，比如你们可能有个用于位置，用于法线，一个用于骨骼
containing different information, like you might have one for like positions, one for normals, one for bones
一个是你们正在处理的，对吧，在这方面，它们仍然在VertexArray中
one for whatever it is that you're dealing with, right, and in that regard, they're still in the VertexArray
但你们要做的是绑定VertexArray，绑定VertexBuffer，设置VertexBuffer的布局
but what you do is you actually bind the VertexArray, bind the VertexBuffer, set the layout for the VertexBuffer
然后你们绑定下个VertexBuffer，用VertexArray设置它的层，仍然是一种绑定，对吧
then you bind your next VertexBuffer, set its layer up with the VertexArray, still kind of bound, right
所以你们可以那样做，但那不是我们今天要讲的内容
so you kind of just do it that way, but that's not something that we're really gonna touch on today
因为使用多个VertexBuffer，不是什么，这是非常常见的，无论如何
because using multiple VertexBuffers isn't something, that's very commonly done, anyway
因为通常更好的做法是把数据放在一个VertexBuffer中，这就是我们一直在做的
because it's usually better to just inter level of your data in a single VertexBuffer, which is what we've been doing
但那是它运行的要点，在IndexBuffer中也是，VertexArray会把它绑定在一起
but that's kind of the gist of how it works, and with an IndexBuffer as well, a VertexArray does actually tie that in
这意味着它也引用那个，所以它不只是VertexBuffers，它们是对应的布局
which means basically that it also references that, so it's not just for VertexBuffers, and they're corresponding layouts
对于IndexBuffer或者元素缓冲区也是这样，对吧，我想提的另一件事是
it's also the case for IndexBuffers, right, for element buffers, one other thing I want to mention is that
在OpenGL 4.5中有一些新函数，也许不确定，我可能会做一个OpenGL系列
there are some new functions in OpenGL 4.5, maybe not sure, I'll probably make an OpenGL series
不管如何，就像这些视频一样，但是有新的函数让它更清晰地联系在一起
like episodes positively about this, anyway, but there are new functions to make this, tying together a little bit more clear
因为它完全，只是很混乱，对吧，OpenGL的接口一般来说并不是很好
because it's completely, just it's messy, right, OpenGL's api in general is not that great
引入这些新函数后，它肯定会更好，但基本上它只是意味着
it definitely is a lot better with introduction of these new functions, but basically it just means that
你们可以将VertexBuffer, layout, IndexBuffer或任何东西绑定到VertexArray中
you can tie together like a VertexBuffer or a layout or an IndexBuffer or anything into a VertexArray
不需要绑定一堆状态，你们只需要指定数组的id, 也就是VertexBuffer的id
without having to bind a bunch of state, you actually just specify the id of the array, the id of the VertexBuffer
它只是把它们联系在一起，这更有意义，这是我们未来可能会探索的东西
it just kind of ties them together that way, which it makes a lot more sense, something that we might explore in the future
但我并不想把这个东西限制在OpenGL 4.5，它很大，而且我自己还没有探索过
but I don't really want to restrict this stuff to I guess OpenGL 4.5, so it's big and it's not really something that I've explored myself yet
但我可能会做一期关于OpenGL的视频，因为我认为那值得探索
but I will probably make an OpenGL episode about that, because I think that's worth kind of exploring
不管怎样，让我们开始，看一下如何构建一个VertexArray类
anyway, let's jump in and take a look at how we can set up a VertexArray class
在这之前，我还想说一件事，在VertexArray中通常不是DirectX中真正存在的东西
before we do that one more thing that I want to say is that, in VertexArray in general are not something that really exists in like DirectX
所以我们在这里要做的选择是，我们如何以一种抽象的方式来构建它，正如我所说的
so the kind of, the choice that we have to make here is, how do we set this up in an abstract way, right, and as I said
现在这个引擎专注于OpenGL，可能有一段时间了，对吧，因为我宁愿像你们知道的那样
right now this engine is focusing on OpenGL, probably for quite a while, right, because I would much rather get like you know
一个完整的游戏引擎，首先使用OpenGL运行，对吧，然后开始在其他api中过滤
a full game engine kind of up and running using OpenGL first, right, and then start filtering in the other apis
因为这将是，这将是最后一次，这样会更好
because this is gonna be, this is gonna take last time, it's gonna just work better
我们会有一个实际的产品来展示比我们一次做所有的api要快得多
and we're gonna have an actual product to show a lot quicker than if we kind of try and just do all the apis at once
所以那就是为什么现在，即使它有点伤害我的内心
so that's why for now, even though it kind of hurts me inside a little bit
我将忽略DirectX以及DirectX是如何处理的，我的意思是，对吧，如果这是一个简单的改变
I'm going to ignore DirectX and how DirectX deals with things, I mean to a point, right, if it's an easy change
那我肯定能挺过去，但这种事不容易
then I'm obviously gonna make it, but something like this is not easy
因为它需要改变很多渲染器API架构
because it requires changing kind of a lot of the renderer api architecture
因为很明显，如果我们强制那样，你们必须创建VertexArrays，然后在其中创建VertexBuffer
because it's like obviously, if we mandate that, you have to create VertexArrays, and then a VertexBuffer for example in your array
这不是DirectX所拥有或需要的，那就需要一些重构来吸引玩家
and that's not something DirectX has or needs, that's going to require some rearchitecture to take players
通常一个快速修复只是基本上有顶点数组，只是在DirectX中什么都不做，对吧
usually a quick fix is just basically having vertex arrays, just do nothing in DirectX, right
所以你们仍然可以在渲染接口不可知的接口中创建个VertexArray，对，这基本上意味着
so you can still create a VertexArray in your kind of api in your render api agnostic api, right, which basically means that
在我们Hazel渲染接口中，仍可以创建VertexArray，在OpenGL中，将创建实际的VertexArray
in our kind of Hazel render api, we can still create a VertexBuffer, sorry, VertexArray, in OpenGL, it will create an actual VertexArray
在DirectX中，实际上什么也做不了，所以这是可以做的一件事，也许是我们现在要做的
in DirectX, they can literally do nothing, so that's one thing that you can do, and probably what we're gonna do right now
因为我们需要让OpenGL运行，不管怎样，让我们深入看看，好吧，上次我们有这个三角形
because we need to get OpenGL to work, anyway, let's dive in and take a look, okay, so last time we had this triangle
我们通过在这里创建这个布局来定义它，对，所以我们在这里定位了颜色
we defined it by just kind of creating this layout here, right, so we had positioned in color over here
但是对我们来说真正令人讨厌的一件事是，这种VertexArray的东西并没有抽象出来，对吧
but the one thing that really kind of sucked for us was this kind of VertexArray stuff was not abstracted whatsoever, right
这也不是布局的东西，所以那就是我们现在要尝试做的，我们要创建一个VertexArray
and neither was this layout stuff, so that's kind of what we're gonna try and do right now, we're gonna create a VertexArray
因此，在Renderer中，我要创建一个新项目，它将是一个VertexArray
so over here in Renderer, I'm gonna make a new item, it's gonna be a VertexArray
然后namespace Hazel，这将是一种，它将遵循相同的方式，我总是很想将其放入缓冲区
and then you know, namespace Hazel, this is gonna be kind of, it's gonna kind of follow the same, I'm always tempted to put it into buffer
或者我没有把它放入缓冲区的原因，因为想把它作为独立文件，在这里有个独立文件
or the reason I didn't put it into buffer, for the reason why I wanted it as a separate had a file here, and like a separate
就像它是一个单独的文件，只是因为当我们复制VertexBuffer时，它会有所不同
like it's a separate file, it's just because it's gonna be a little bit different, when we just copy VertexBuffer
但会有一点不同，因为我甚至不确定我是否想长期保持它，或者也许可以称之为别的东西
but it's gonna be a little bit different, because I'm not even sure if I want to keep it long term, or maybe we can call it something else
所以我现在真的不想没有商量，我想，我甚至不知道我包含什么，可能有点多
so I don't really want to kind of deal without I guess for now, I don't even know what I'm including, probably do I need much
我想我将包括缓冲区，Renderer/Buffer.h，所以现在我只是将其分开
I guess I'll include Buffer, Renderer/Buffer.h, so for now I'm kind of just keeping it separated
因为我不确定，但是它的未来会是什么，所以有个VertexArray，我们将有个析构函数
because I'm not sure but what its future is gonna be, so we have a VertexArray, we'll have a destructor
这又是一种平台，与渲染api无关的接口，就创建而言
this is again the kind of platform, the render api agnostic, like interface, in terms of creation
我认为可以像那样创建它，实际上不需要任何参数，SetLayout不会成为一件事
I think just you can just create it like that, doesn't really need any parameters, SetLayout not gonna be a thing
我们能做的就是给它添加一个缓冲区，所以补充一下，我只是在想最好的方法，我们会有
what we can do is actually add a buffer to it, so Add, I'm just thinking the best way to do this, we'll have we'll have
将有个VertexBuffer，所以virtual void AddVertexBuffer，
we'll have um a VertexBuffer, so virtual void AddVertexBuffer
然后只接收VertexBuffer，好了，所以我们不
and then this will just take in a VertexBuffer, okay, so we don't
我们真正想要的是一个引用，我将来可能会谈论这个，现在我们只需要一个共享指针
what we actually want to take in is a ref, I might talk about this in the future, for now we're just going to take in a shared pointer
资源在Hazel内部的工作方式基本上是一切，每一种资源相关的东西
the way that resources are going to work inside Hazel is there basically everything, every resource kind of related thing
就像VertexBuffer和IndexBuffer，纹理，着色器一样，所有这些东西都将被引用计数，对吧
like a VertexBuffer and IndexBuffer, a Texture, a Shader, all that kind of stuff is going to be referenced counted, right
所以它们基本上是共享指针，现在如果我真的像学究的，非常具体的性能和所有这些
so they're basically going to be shared pointers, now if I was really like pedantic and really specific about performance and all of that
我可能想创建一个侵入性的引用计数系统，但我不喜欢，我实际上不认为共享指针
I'd probably want to create an intrusive reference counting system, but I don't like, I don't actually think shared pointer
特别是如果实际的引用计数块在内存中排成一行，我实际上并不认为它的性能会更差
especially if the actual reference count block is in line in memory, I don't actually think that it's gonna perform worse
所以现在，只需要处理这个问题，但是只需要const std::shared_ptr VertexBuffer
so for now, we're just gonna deal with that, right, but what we're gonna just take a  const shared_ptr VertexBuffer
我们就称之为，我想vertexBuffer，好吧，将来我们可能会做的只是
and we'll just call this, I guess vertexBuffer, okay, and in the future what we might do is just kind of
因为实现可能会更改，并且我们不想在任何地方更改代码，所以我通常喜欢更改
because the implementation might change, and we don't want to change our code anywhere, I usually like changing
就像基本上将实际的类型名称更改为其他名称一样，但是我们将在另一期中讨论
like basically changing the actual type name to be something else, but we will talk about that in another episode
所以我们会有AddVertexBuffer，我们会有，我们会有今天他们有，我们也会有索引缓冲区
so we'll have AddVertexBuffer,  we'll have, we'll have kind of in today they have had, we'll have an IndexBuffer as well
AddIndexBuffer，它将接收IndexBuffer，我们实际上可能会拥有，并且我们将摆脱常量
AddIndexBuffer, which will take in an IndexBuffer, we'll actually probably have, and we'll get rid of constant
我们可能会有某种所有权实际发生，我们将有Bind和Unbind，现在在前面的类中
we'll probably have some kind of ownership actually taking place, we'll have Bind and Unbind, now in the previous classes
我们也有Bind和Unbind，这不是必需的，但是对于VertexArray，实际上确实想解绑它们
we also have bind and unbind, it's not that necessary, but for VertexArrays, you actually kind of do want to unbind them potentially
除非你们喜欢，否则就像我说的那样，这对测试有好处，我可以告诉你们我的意思
unless you like, it's again as I said it's good for testing, and I can, I can kind of show you what I mean by that
也许在另一期视频中，如果你们感兴趣，关于为什么我在任何地方都写Unbind
maybe in another video, if you're interested, as to why on earth I write unbind everywhere
我的意思是我不在我的代码中写它，我的意思是
I mean I don't write it in my code I mean
好吧，但是为什么api支持它，但这可能是我们稍后讨论的内容，我们也必须包含memory
well but why the api supports it, but that might be something that we talk about later, we'll have to include memory as well
那是共享指针，好了，酷，所以我们有VertexArray
that's the shared pointer, okay, cool, so there we have VertexArray
让我们复制这个文件，让我们为它创建一个cpp文件，VertexArray.cpp
let's grab this file, let's make a cpp file for it, VertexArray.cpp
当然，我犯了一个输入错误，那不是我的错，我发誓字母r没有打两次，我们将包含hzpch
and of course I made a type error, that's not my fault, I swear the letter r didn't punch in twice, we'll include hzpch
和VertexArray.h，namespace Hazel，然后我们真的只有Create函数，当然我会复制并粘贴
and VertexArray.h, namespace Hazel, and then we really just have the Create function, of course I'll copy and paste that
我们将从Buffer.cpp复制并粘贴此实现，因此现在这里的典型情况
and we will copy and paste the implementation of this from Buffer.cpp, so typical scenario here now
到目前为止，我一直在使用指针，好了，因此可以在此处返回共享指针，并且可以处理引用
I have been using pointers up until now, okay, so we could return a shared pointer here, and we could deal with refs
但是显然，你们也可以返回像这样的原始指针，然后将其捕获到共享指针或唯一指针中
but obviously you can also return a raw pointer like this, and then capture it into either a either a shared pointer or or a unique pointer
那就是为什么在我们可能像我说的那样切换到更多的引用系统之前，因为这就是我们要
so that's why for now before we maybe switched to more of a ref system as I said, because that's what we're gonna
那就是我们的方向，如果你们想自己去做，对吧，现在你们绝对可以
that's kind of where we're heading towards, if you want to do that yourself, right, now you absolutely can
但是因为那是我们以后的方向，所以我不想打扰我想现在的改变
but because that's where we're heading towards, I'm not gonna bother kind of changing that I guess now
所以这将返回一个OpenGLVertexArray，那对我来说看起来相当不错
so this will return an OpenGLVertexArray, and that looks pretty good to me I think
所以现在在Platform，Platform/OpenGL在这里
so now in Platform, Platform/OpenGL over here
我要添加OpenGLVertexArray.h和OpenGLVertexArray.cpp
I'm going to add OpenGLVertexArray.h and OpenGLVertexArray.cpp
包含hzpch，而不是handed_coordinate_space
this will include hzpch, not the handed_coordinate_space
以及OpenGLVertexArray.h，namespace Hazel
and the OpenGLVertexArray header file, namespace Hazel
那么包含Hazel/Renderer/VertexArray.h，然后为什么它现在在输入那个，不是那么好
okay, so include Hazel, oops, Hazel/Renderer/Vertex array.h, and then why it's typing right now, it's not that great
所以当早上试着做这种事情的时候会发生什么，所以去VertexArray，几乎复制了大部分
so what happens when you try and do this kind of stuff in the morning, so let's go to our VertexArray I guess, pretty much copy most of this
我将复制整个类来询问，所以将会有一个OpenGLVertexArray，它将是一个VertexArray
I'll just copy the whole class to be asked, so there's gonna be an OpenGLVertexArray, which will be a VertexArray
所以我们要做的是，把它放进去，让我们看看，所以我们会改变它来看到所有的覆盖
so what we're gonna do is, so just pop that in, let's see, so we'll change this to see override for all of them
然后我们仍然有我们的Bind和Unbind，这很好，好的，很酷，然后我们不需要Create
and then we've still got our Bind and Unbind, which is good, okay, cool, and then we don't need to Create obviously
所以就我们实际保存的东西而言，我们确实想要有某种列表
so in terms of stuff that we're actually keeping, so we do actually want to have some kind of list I guess
shared_ptr VertexBuffer的向量，好了，所以实际上包含了对放入的每个VertexBuffer的引用
so vector of shared_ptr VertexBuffer, okay, so we actually contain references to every VertexBuffer that we actually put in
所以就像OpenGL在内部做的一样，我们在这里模仿在CPU上镜像
so just like the just like OpenGL is doing internally, we're kind of mimicking on mirroring that on the CPU here
通过拥有所有VertexBuffers和IndexBuffers的列表，不要相信可以有多个IndexBuffer
by just having a list of all VertexBuffers and IndexBuffers, don't believe you can have more than one IndexBuffer
老实说，我认为我以前从未这样做过，所以我可能会将其更改为SetIndexBuffer，我可能错了
to be honest, I don't think I've ever done that before, so I might change this to SetIndexBuffer, I might be wrong
也许这是可能的，但老实说，我以前从未见过，我以前从未做过
maybe it's possible somehow, but to be honest, I've never seen it before, I've never done it before
所以现在，我们只调用这个SetIndexBuffer，我们就有一个
so for now, we'll just call this SetIndexBuffer, and we'll just have one
所以我向你们描述的这种行为是如何运行的，你们可以看到我们现在在代码中重新创建它
so that behavior that I kind of described to you guys on how this works, you can see that we're kind of recreating it in code now
这是所有这一切的目标，所以让我们看看我们在这里有什么，什么都没有，这很好
which is kind of the goal of all of this, so let's see what we have here, nothing, which is good
我将在这里使用visual assist来创建所有方法实现，在这里我们拥有一切
I'm going to use visual assist here to just create all the method implementations, and here we have everything
所以我们显然也需要一个构造函数，所以创建构造函数，接下来是什么，所以在构造函数中
so we obviously need to have a constructor as well, so let's just have a constructor, and what's next, so in the constructor
我们想创建一切，如果看Buffer，可以看到，对不起，VertexBuffer，哦，对不起GLBuffer
we want to officer create everything, if I look at just Buffer, you can see that we, sorry, VertexBuffer, oh sorry GL OpenGLBuffer
可以看到我们只是在这里创建所有的东西，对吧，我会用VertexArray做同样的事情
you can see that we simply just create everything kind of here, right, I'm gonna do the same thing with VertexArrays
所以在这里，在VertexArray中，调用glCreateVertexArrays，然后输入1，m_RendererID
so over here, in my VertexArray, I'm just gonna call glCreateVertexArrays, and then I guess I'll tape in one, and then m_RendererID
对m_RendererID使用什么，因为总是忘记，它只是无符号int，所以正如我所说，可能会像
and what do we use for m_RendererID, because I always forget, it's just a unsigned int, so as I said, we probably will end up like
把它打成别的东西，最后就是那样，现在我似乎弄错了，也许
type daffing that into something else, the final is just that, now that I seem to have gotten this wrong maybe
所以让我们来看看这个，没错，也许那只是不起作用，因为我没包含glad之类的东西
so let's take a look at this, that's right, maybe that's just not working, because of me not including glad or something like that
可以创建VertexArray，就是那样，对于绑定，只绑定VertexArray，所以glBindVertexArray
yep okay, cool, so we can create a VertexArray, and that's pretty much it, for binding, we just bind a VertexArray, so glBindVertexArray
对吧，它只是m_RendererID，对于Unbind，我们再次为VertexBuffer绑定0
right, and it's just m_RendererID, for Unbind, again we just bind 0 for a VertexBuffer
所以我们需要做的实际上是确保数组绑定，现在我想有人问了
so what we need to do is actually make sure the arrays bound, now I think someone asked the question of
为什么我不这样在这里调用Bind，我不这样做的原因是因为我，我通常不喜欢
why I don't just call Bind here like this, the reason I don't do that is because I, I don't generally like to
就像将OpenGL调用与我自己的调用混合一样，显然在某些情况下
like mix OpenGL calls with just my own calls, obviously in some situations
如果你们正在做非常复杂的事情，这是必要的
it's necessary, if you're doing really complex stuff
但是，如果只是这样的一行，我宁愿把它写在这里
but if it's just one line like this, I would much rather have it actually just be written here
这样做的原因是，就像将来一样，我们可能会添加要绑定的东西，对吧
and the reason for that is that a lot like in the future, we might add stuff to bind, right
我们可能会添加一些东西来解绑，或者像你们知道的那样，本质上跟踪或者分析目的
we might add stuff to unbind or whatever for like you know, tracking essentially or profiling purposes
我不一定希望它将自己注册为实际绑定，就好像它是由游戏或渲染器调用的一样
I don't necessarily want this to register itself as an actual bind, as if it's been called by the game or by the renderer
因为这是api内部的东西，对吧，所以因为这是api内部的东西，你们知道，这完全可以调用
because this is kind of api internal things, right, so because this is api internal things, you know, this is totally fine to call
而且我绝对不希望此函数不必要地开始分支到一堆其他函数中
and I definitely don't want this function to start branching out into a bunch of other functions needlessly
如果有必要确定，对吧，就像我有一个名为AddVertexAndIndexBuffer的函数，对吧
if it's necessary for sure, right, like if I had a function called AddVertexAndIndexBuffer, right
它两者都做了，我肯定称之为，我不会写，也不会复制和粘贴整个OpenGL代码
and it just did both, I definitely call this, and this I wouldn't write, I wouldn't copy and paste the whole OpenGL code
但是在这种情况下，它只是一个简单的绑定，不需要，只是将其转移到不同的函数中
there but in this situation, it's just a simple bind, no need to just divert it into a different function
通过这样做使事情变得复杂，嗯，好吧，那么一旦我们绑定了VertexArray
and just complicate things by doing that essentially, um okay, so then once we bound our VertexArray
实际上想要做的是绑定VertexBuffer，所以在这种情况下，当然会调用vertexBuffer->Bind()
what we actually want to do is bind our VertexBuffer, so in this case of course, I will call vertexBuffer->Bind()
因为你们知道，这是在处理一个实际的api对象，它不是在处理，它是在一种类上
because you know, this is dealing with an actual api object here, it's not dealing with, it's on a kind of class
我绝对不会做任何像glBindVertexBuffer这样的，然后再vertexBuffer->GetRendererID
I'm definitely not gonna do anything like glBindVertexBuffer, and then vertexBuffer GetRendererId or something disgusting like that
所以我们肯定会绑定它，现在我需要做的是，一旦我限制了
so we're definitely gonna bind it, now what I need to do, once I've bounded
如果我们回到Application，我基本上需要做所有这些事情，所以很容易做到
if we go back to Application is I need to basically do all of this stuff, so pretty easy to do
我可以复制此代码并将其粘贴到此处，因为那是一种想法，VertexBuffers布局在这更改
I can just copy this code and paste it into here, right, because that's kind of the idea, and VertexBuffers a layout is going to get changed here
现在，这个着色器类型现在再次，复制它，我们最终可能会生存在某种OpenGL中
now this shader type again at the moment, we're going to grab it and we're going to eventually might live inside some kind of OpenGL
就像Shader类一样，但是现在我们将它放在这里的VertexArray的顶部，好了
like Shader class, but for now we're just going to put it into the top our VertexArray over here, okay
现在确保这是空格，好了，就那样，那就是我们要做的一切
now make sure that's tabs across, all right, and that's it, that's literally all that we have to do
显然，我还想实际将VertexBuffer添加到我们的VertexBuffers列表中
obviously I also want to actually add the VertexBuffer to our list of VertexBuffers
因此我将输入m_VertexBuffers.push_back(vertexBuffer)，好了
so I'll type in m_VertexBuffers.push_back(vertexBuffer), okay
现在我们将它添加到VertexBuffers列表中，但就那样，对吧，如果突然决定这样，那很好
and now we'll just add it to our list of VertexBuffers, but that's it, right, if we suddenly decide that like that's, that's fine
我们想用不同的布局添加另一个像VertexBuffer之类的，完全没问题，它会运行，好了
we want to add another like VertexBuffer or something to this with a different layout, that's totally fine, and it will work, okay
就因为我们是这样做的，好吧，酷，最后，没有必要解绑任何东西
just because we're doing it kind of this way, okay, cool, and then at the end of this, it's not really necessary to unbind anything
我现在只是在想这个，我不认为我们需要，没有什么会出错
I'm just thinking about this now, I don't think that we need to, nothing's going to go wrong
如果在解绑之前绑定了另个VertexArray，我不认为，我认为是将其绑定在一起的实际绑定
if you bind another VertexArray before unbinding this, I don't think, I think it's the actual binding that ties it together
这就是为什么api很糟糕，那就是为什么改变了它，但我认为它应该是安全的，我不认为
see, this is why the api is terrible, and that's why they changed it, but so I think it should be safe, I don't think
突然，它将属于一个不同的VertexArray之类，在这里，我们将再次复制这个
suddenly it's going to belong to a different VertexArray or anything like that, here again we're going to copy this
这真的很简单，基本上只是复制这个，对吧，所以我们会复制那个
this is really easy, it's basically just copying this, right, so we'll copy yep that
然后，我们正在做indexBuffer->Bind()，而不是vertexBuffer->Bind()，对吧
and then instead of vertexBuffer->Bind(), we're doing indexBuffer->Bind(), right
然后实际上就是那样，对，就是那样
and then that's actually it, right, that's that's it
我们不需要做任何其他事情，就像显然会把它添加到，我们会在IndexBuffer中设置它
we don't need to do anything else, like obviously we'll add it to our, we'll set it in our IndexBuffer
不知道为什么被称为IndexBuffers，通常情况下，vector会将其改为IndexBuffer，但仅此而已
I don't know why it's called IndexBuffers, because it usually, vector will change that to IndexBuffer, but that's it, right
这个单独绑定它，然后只是绑定VertexArray
this alone binding it, and then just binding the VertexArray
然后绑定一个关联到VertexArray的IndexBuffer
then binding an IndexBuffer associated to the VertexArray
我知道这很疯狂，我讨厌它，所以几乎所有人都这么做
I know it's crazy, I hate it, so it's pretty much everyone else
那就是为什么他们改变了它，或者试图创建它
that's why they kind of changed it or try to make it
他们没有改变它，但是他们做了额外的api，这样你们就可以写代码了，这样会更有可读性
they didn't change it, but they made additional api, so that you could write that code instead, that would be more readable
这个以后会讲到，但那就是OpenGL传统的运行方式，好了，很有趣，我想应该是那样吧
which we will explore as I said in the future, but that's how OpenGL traditionally works, so there you go, fun times, I think that should be it
现在看下在实际的Application类中能做什么，这个这个现在没有了，我们会保留这段代码
so now let's take a look at what we can do inside our actual Application class, so and this this is now gone, right, we'll keep this code
因为已经设置好了，这个去掉，我想在Application中也有个绑定VertexArray，在Update中
because we're setting that up, this should be gone, right, and I think we also have a bind VertexArray up in the Application, sorry in the Update
或者渲染任何在运行循环中调用的函数，在Run中，我们要做的是到这里，我们要创建一个
or Render whatever function is called in the run loop, in the Run function, so what we'll do is go over here, we'll create a
我说过，我们会习惯创建共享指针，但在我们正确设置之前
and as I said, we're gonna kind of get used to creating shared pointers, but until we have that properly set up
我想坚持这里的内容，我们创建一个VertexArray，我把它放在这里
I kind of want to just stick with what we have here, so we'll create a VertexArray, I'll put it up here
因为它是这两个的父结点，我们有一个VertexArray，这是一个唯一指针，就像其他指针一样
because it's kind of the parent of these 2, so we have a VertexArray, which is a unique point of just like everything else
我们会包含那个，然后m_VertexArray.reset()，那就是简单创建它，可以写Create
we'll include that, and then we'll do m_VertexArray.reset(), and that's us simply creating it, I can write the world create
所以我们已经创建了它，搞定，对吧，现在我们要做的是，并不重要
so we've created it, that's done, right, now what we need to do is again, doesn't really matter
我们可以创建任何我们想要的东西，我们可以用任何东西，任何我们想要的东西
we can create anything we want, we can by anything, anything we want
现在这是危险的，这是我有点喜欢解绑的地方
now this is dangerous, and this is where I some somewhat like unbinding
因为如果你们离开这个边界，绑定其他东西，这显然发生在我们创建VertexBuffer时
because if you leave this bound and you bind something else, which happens obviously, when we create the VertexBuffer
它们突然联系在一起，有点危险，因为你们知道，就像我说的
they're suddenly associated together, that's a little bit dangerous, okay, because you know, as I said
关联在一起只是绑定另一个VertexBuffer，同时绑定一个VertexArray
the thing that association together is just binding another VertexBuffer, while a VertexArray bound
那有点危险，我不喜欢那样，因为就像我们说的，你们知道，有这样的感觉很好
that's kind of dangerous, I don't like that, because as we said, you know, it's nice to just have, you know
我们有一个特定的函数，我们想要调用它，基本上就是那样
we have a specific function here that we want to call, which is basically just saying that
我们想要添加一个VertexBuffer到一个VertexArray，对吧
we want to add a VertexBuffer to a VertexArray, right
目前是可以的，我们要把所有东西都改成共享指针
and it's currently okay, we will have to change everything to shared points
它也会运行，非常干净，所以这是一个很好的时机，这就变成了共享指针
as well as it's gonna work, very cleanly, so this could be a good time to do that, so this just becomes shared pointer
没有什么改变，顺便说一下，这个变成了共享指针，那就是改变的结束，那么我刚才说的是
nothing really changes, by the way, this just becomes shared pointer, and that's the end of the change really, so what was I saying yeah
如果添加VertexBuffer，在这一点上，它会找到VertexArray和VertexBuffer，然后那样
so if we do add, if we add the VertexBuffer, right, at this point, it finds the VertexArray and the VertexBuffer, and then thus that
访问布局，并将它们链接在一起，但那实际上已经发生了，为什么，因为有VertexArray
you know access layout and links them together, but that's actually already happened, why, because we've credited a VertexArray
很明显，VertexArray的Create函数，你们可以看到，已经绑定了它，对吧，完成了
and obviously the Create function for VertexArray, as you can see, has bound it, right, it's done
实际上，它没有，因为我们没有调用Bind，很有趣，那可能会拯救我们
actually no, it hasn't, because we haven't called bind, that's interesting, so that might actually save us
不管怎样，它对VertexBuffer是这样，如果看这，因为要上传数据，那就是原因，除非解绑
but anyway, it does for VertexBuffer, obviously if we look in this, right, because we have to upload the data, that's why, so unless we unbind this
它会把自己绑定到VertexArray，那就是我们最终会遇到的情况
it's going to kind of bind itself to the VertexArray, so that's kind of the situation that we're kind of that we end up with
有点烦人，因为OpenGL，但不管怎样，我不担心那些
which is a little bit annoying, because of OpenGL, but anyway, I'm going to not worry about any of that
因为我不认为，它真的会阻止任何运行
because I didn't think that, it's going to actually stop anything from working
我想我们可能会有点困惑，并以调试应用程序的状态结束
I think that we might just be somewhat confused, and end up kind of debugging, the state of our application
比我们预期的要多一点，否则，如果API更好，也意味着人们可能会误用它
a bit more than we would, otherwise, if the api was better, also means people might misuse this
这对我来说很难尝试和预测，老人会滥用它，所以我会让它保持原样，看看会发生什么
it's hard for me to try and anticipate, old people misusing this, so I'll kind of leave it as is, and see what happens
基于这种API在我们引擎中的使用，在未来我们可能会开始解绑
and based on the usage of this kind of api inside our engine, in the future we may start unbinding things
或者处理一些不同的方式，总之，我们创建了VertexArray
or dealing with some kind of different way of doing things, anyway, so VertexArray, we create the VertexArray
没关系，我们在这里做，顺便说一下，可以在任何地方
doesn't matter that, we're doing it here, by the way, can be anywhere
我们在后面添加VertexBuffer到VertexArray
we add the VertexBuffer to the VertexArray after
在它被创建之后，在我们设置了布局之后，那很重要，我们会去掉那个作用域
after it's been created, and after we've set a layout, okay, so that's important, and we'll kind of get rid of that scope
我认为那很重要，在布局设置之后做这个，因为如果在布局设置之前做，它什么都不会做
I think that's important, that we do this after the layout has been set, because if we do it before it's not gonna do anything, right
因为你们可以在这里看到，它实际上执行了这段代码，这取决于布局，所以那很重要
because you can see that here, it actually does this code, which depends on the layout, so that's important
如果它没有布局或图层为空，你们可以在这里断言，就像什么都没有一样
if it has no layout or layer as empty, where you could assert over here, and say that like there's nothing
布局中没有元素，实际上这可能是我想要做的，因此我们写入HZ_CORE_ASSERT
there's no elements in the layout, in fact that's probably something that I actually do want to do, so we'll say I just HZ_CORE_ASSERT
我们写入vertexBuffer->GetLayout().GetElements().size()，对吧
and we'll say basically the vertexBuffer->GetLayout().GetElements().size(), right
所以基本上元素的大小不能为0，否则你们就可以说VertexBuffer没有布局
so basically the size of the elements has to not be 0, right, otherwise well you could say that the VertexBuffer has no layout
所以我们就会说VertexBuffer没有布局，我们会把它放在函数的最前面
so we'll say VertexBuffer has no layout, okay, and we'll put that as the very first thing in the function
好了，那只是以防万一的一个小保护，我们可以在一分钟内测试一下以防你们不小心那样做
alright, that's just a little guard in case, and we can test that out in a minute in case you accidentally do that
因为在那种情况下，这将不起作用，即使API看起来是可以的
because in that case, this won't work, even though the api might seem like it does
好了，顺便说一下，要让它起作用，你们可以进入VertexBuffer
okay, now again what you could do to make that work by the way is you could into the VertexBuffer
你们可以添加一个引用到VertexBuffer属于的VertexArray
you could add a reference to the VertexArray, the VertexBuffer belongs to
我的意思是当你们添加一个VertexBuffer
so what I mean by that is when you add a VertexBuffer
它只是在VertexBuffer本身中设置它的父类，所以这个函数会继续，说
it just sets its parent essentially inside the VertexBuffer itself, so this function just goes ahead, and says you know
你们不会再给它传常数了，我猜函数会直接说VertexBuffer
you wouldn't pass it by constant,  anymore I guess the function goes ahead and just says VertexBuffer
VertexArray或等于这个，这样它就有了那个链接，然后当你们更新VertexBuffer的布局时
VertexArray or VertexArray or equals of this, and that way it's got that connection, and then when you update the VertexBuffer's layout
对吧，你们就可以更新VertexArray，它是它的一部分，如果它是多个的话
right, you can update the VertexArray that, it's part of or VertexArrays that, it's part of if it's multiple
所以那是值得思考的，但不是我真正想做的，最后我们创建IndexBuffer
so that's food for thought, but not something that I really want to do, and then finally we create our IndexBuffer
我还想把它加到这里，好了，酷，那么就是AddIndexBuffer(m_IndexBuffer)
and I also want to add that into here, okay, cool, so AddIndexBuffer(m_IndexBuffer)
那完全不是一个东西，因为它叫set，好了，酷，继续，现在我们可以解绑了
and that's totally not a thing, because it's called set, okay, cool, there we go, so now the idea is we can unbind everything
我们可以创建一大堆这样的东西，对吧，在这个例子中很难演示，我猜是因为它太简单了
we can create a whole bunch of these, right, it's kind of hard to demonstrate in this one example, just because it is so easy I guess
从某种意义上说，这很简单我们只是创建了所有东西中的一个，但如果我们有多个
alright, it is so simple in a sense that we're just creating one of everything, but if we had multiple
我们可以继续，继续授予所有其他的，假设我们正在加载一堆网格
we could just go ahead, and keep granting all of our other ones, let's just say we're loading a bunch of meshes
我们可以在这里创建并加载所有的网格，然后当我们绑定它
we could, you know, create and load all of our meshes here, and then when we bind it
那才是它真正开始发挥作用的时候，使用所有与它相关的状态
that's when it's actually going to kick in and use all the state that we've associated with it
那么在这里，显然我们要做m_VertexArray->Bind()，然后渲染，就使用glDrawElements
now so over here, obviously we're going to do m_VertexArray->Bind(), right, and then we're just gonna render, using glDrawElements
就像我们有所有这些次数一样，使用IndexBuffer中的计数，我想差不多就是那样了
just like we have all of this time, right, using the count from the IndexBuffer, I think that is pretty much it
所以应该能运行这段代码，希望它能编译，希望它能按预期运行，不，它甚至不能编译
so we should be able to just run this code, and hopefully it compiles, and hopefully it runs as expected, no, it doesn't even compile
VertexArray重新定义，这是因为以前有个无符号int，叫做VertexArray，现在可以删掉
okay, so VertexArray redefinition ya, that's because we used to have this unsigned int called VertexArray, we can delete that now
让我们继续再试一次，这里有另一个错误，好的，这个，是了，需要包含Hazel/Platform
let's go ahead and try again, okay, here's another error on it, okay, this, yep we need to include Hazel/Platform
它不是在Hazel里面吗，它只是Platform，我想我上次也很惊讶
is it not inside Hazel, it's just Platform, I think I was surprised by that last time as well
很好，在哪里知道你们自己的代码显示，呃，f5，我们应该会看到和上次结果完全一样
great, where to know your own code based shown er, f5, and well we should see is exactly the same result as last time her play yep
很酷，一切看起来都很正常，我们可以继续创建另一个版本，我想看看它是如何运行的
cool, everything looks like it works, we could go ahead and just create another version, I guess and see how that works
我想我会快速地做一下，所以我们会试着创造一些完全不同的东西
I guess I will go ahead and do that just quickly, so we'll try and create something completely different
为了测试，我说过我也会测试断言，所以让我们在实际设置布局之前尝试添加VertexBuffer
I guess to test us out, I said I would also test out the asset, so let's try and add the VertexBuffer before we actually set the layout
如果它让我们没有抱怨，因为他没有，它说，上面没有布局，对吧
so if it lets us without complaining, and because he doesn't, it says that, that above has no layout, right
所以它断言，然后我们就像，哦，我们一定还没有为VertexBuffer设置布局，好了，很好
so it asserts, and then we're like, oh, we must not have set a layout yet for our VertexBuffer, okay, great
让我们继续创建一个正方形，我基本上需要这三个，现在那在技术上是不正确的
so let's go ahead and create maybe a square, so I'll basically need all three of these, right, now that's not technically true
现在需要计数，因为需要知道计数，IndexBuffers计数，这是可以添到VertexArrays的东西
now I need the count, right, because I need to know the count, the IndexBuffers count, right, that is something we could add to VertexArrays
对吧，它故意像VertexArray，因为我们没有api来获取
right, right, it like, it's deliberately like to the VertexArray, alright, because we don't have an api to retrieve
它现在存储了什么，我将继续添加它
what it stores at the moment, I'm going to go ahead and add that though
所以我们会说virtual const std::vector>&
so we'll say virtual std::vector, std::shared_ptr, VertexBuffer, all right, there's gonna be a const and a const reference
GetVertexBuffers() const = 0，我们会有相同的东西，但不是向量，那将用于IndexBuffer
GetVertexBuffers const equals 0, all right, and we'll have the same thing, but not the vector, and that will be for our IndexBuffer
所以是IndexBuffer，GetIndexBuffer，我们会复制这个，我们会进入OpenGLVertexArray
so IndexBuffer, GetIndexBuffer, right, and we'll copy this, and we'll go into our OpenGLVertexArray
我们再来创建这些，我把这个移开，这将是一个，这将返回VertexBuffer
and we'll just make these again, let me just move this out of the way, and this will just be a, this will just return VertexBuffer
对吧，我们在这里得到了整个集合，这将返回IndexBuffer，好了，酷
right, so we get the whole collection here, and this will return IndexBuffer, okay, cool
现在我们的api能够做到这一点，这很重要，因为我们现在要用到它
so now our api's capable of that, which is important, because we're gonna use it now
那么在这里，我们不需要创建这三个，我们只需要VertexArray，对吧
so over here, instead of creating like all three of these, we can just say we want the VertexArray, right
我将它命名为m_SquareVertexArray，因为它是，这个叫做squareVA, squareVertex，对吧
I'll call this something like m_SquareVertexArray, because it is our, this is called squareVA, square vertex, right, right
这将是，我们要在这里绘制一个正方形而不是三角形，所以我们要做的是，我们要在这里
this is gonna be, we're gonna make a square instead of a triangle here, so what we'll do is we'll kind of go over here
我们已经有了着色器，在着色器之前，我来创建这个，对吧
we've got the shader, maybe before the shader, I'll create this, right
就是reset，然后VertexArray::Create()
so .reset, and then VertexArray::Create()
我必须创建一个VertexBuffer，所以我们会看到
I'll have to create a VertexBuffer, so we'll see
std::shared_ptr squareVB = std::make_shared()
然后我们要把顶点绘制进去，我们复制粘贴这些顶点
and then we'll have to take in the vertices, so we'll copy and paste these vertices
这里我要做的和之前有点不同，因为那是测试的重点
and what I want to do here is a little bit different than before, because that's kind of the point of testing this
这个实际上不会有任何顶点颜色，这有点争议
this is actually not going to have any vertex colors at all, now this is going to be a little bit controversial
因为着色器实际上需要顶点，它需要那个颜色，你们必须使用不同的着色器
because the shader actually expects vertex, it needs that color, right, you have to either use a different shader or whatever
因为，否则它就不能运行，我们要做的就是快速创建一个新的着色器
because it's, otherwise it's just not gonna work, so what we might do is just quickly create a new shader
或者我们可以直接去看看，我想如果已经设置好了，可能不太好，可以添加个统一变量
or we can just go ahead and check to see, I guess if that's been set or not, which might not be great though, we could add a uniform
我们可以做一些事情，但我们会看看，如果不提供顶点数据，它会渲染一个黑色正方形
there's a few things we could do, but we'll just see if it may be, renders a black square for us, if we don't supply that vertex data
但它有点，有点脏，你们不应该这样做，所以我可能会快速复制粘贴，创建新的着色器
but it's a bit, it's a bit dirty, you shouldn't be doing things like that, so maybe I'll just quickly copy in paste making new shader
我可能会这样做，我们粘贴复制以便快速分享，还有vertexSrc
I'll probably will do that actually, let's copy in paste to share it quickly, and vertexSrc
你们知道两个，因为我很有想象力，而且我想让它继续，它就会这样，它就会这样
you know two, because I'm that imaginative, and also I just want to get this going, and this will just do that, and it will just have that
那就是唯一的区别，我们去掉了v_Color，对吧，它就只有属性位置
that's the only difference really, so we've got rid of v_Color, right, it's just got the attribute position
然后颜色会被设置为，我想是这个，但我们可以设置一个平面颜色，如果我们想，让我们的
and then the color is just gonna be set to the, I guess this, but we could set a flat color, if we wanted to, let's make our
我们把它设为蓝色，好吧，这就把它设为蓝色，我们也把它去掉
let's make it like blue I guess, okay, so this just sets it to blue, and we'll get rid of that as well
好了，酷，然后这就是第二个着色器，m_Shader2，我和你们一样讨厌这个命名，别担心
okay, cool, and then this will be ours our second shader, m_Shader2, I hate this naming as much as you do, don't worry
我们复制这个，就叫m_Shader2，不行，不好意思，叫它blueShader，因为我不能这样叫它
we'll copy this m_Shader2, I can't, I just can't, I'm sorry, we're gonna call it blueShader, because I can't just call it that
blueShaderVertexSrc，我只记得我必须把这个推到github
blueShaderVertexSrc, I just remember that I have to push this to github
所以我不可能用这么糟糕的命名来写代码，更有描述性，如果必要的话，使用更长的变量名
so there's no way that I'm doing code with such bad naming, be more descriptive, use longer variable names, if you have to
相信我，这是最好的方法，好了，现在有两个不同的东西，所以就像我说的一个正方形
trust me, it's the best way to go, okay, so now we have 2 different things here as well, so this is just going to be as I said a square
所以我们不做这些，在0.5处也有这个，只调整这些顶点，所以我们处理的是一个正方形
so instead of doing all of this, we also have this at 0.5, we'll just adjust these vertices, so that we're dealing with a square
这是3x4，这是负的x，对我来说，那是一个正方形
there's gonna be 3x4, and this will be negative on the x, okay, that looks like a square to me
很好，现在我们要创建那个VertexBuffer，就像我们做的那样，我们不能这样做
good, now we're going to create that VertexBuffer, and just like we did with, oh we can't actually make it this way
顺便说一下，因为它没有构造函数，所以我们可以，我们可以就这样留着它，然后重置它
by the way, because it doesn't have a constructor, so we can, we can just, we can either just leave it like that, and then reset it
或者我们可以使用VertexBuffer::Create()来创建共享
or we can probably do make shared maybe with VertexBuffer::Create()
然后要输入顶点，也就是squareVertices，然后进行sizeof，也就是sizeof(squareVertices)
and then we'll have to put in the vertices, which are our squareVertices and in the sizeof them, so sizeof squareVertices
好了，那应该没问题，然后我们需要创建一个布局并设置它
okay, and that should be okay, great, so then we need to set, we need to create a layout and set it
并将它添加到VertexBuffer中，作为关键变量，VertexArray就像这里，squareVBLayout
and add it to the VertexBuffer, as fatality, the VertexArray is like here, so we'll say squareVBLayout
对吧，我的意思是你们可以把它放在这里，顺便说一下，如果真的想，可以像这样写代码
right, I mean you could just put this right in here, by the way, if you really wanted to, you could just write code like this
对吧，那是可行的，为什么要这么做，只是为了好玩，这样你们就能看到，两种不同的方法
right, and that would work, why we might just do that, just for fun, so that you guys can see, two different ways of doing it
我们可以把布局设置成那样，这也会让它看起来很酷，那么这就是我们的布局
but yeah we can just set the layout to be that, which is also kind of makes it look really nice, cool, and so there's our layout
然后我们把它加到squareVA中，对吧，我们要做的是squareVB，好了
and then we're adding it to the squareVA, right, and what we're doing is squareVB, okay
很好，现在我们基本上已经把所有权转移到这个VertexBuffer，因为它是个共享指针
cool, so now we've basically transferred our ownership into this VertexBuffer, because it's a shared pointer
这个作用域实际上会过期，但作用域中的这个变量显然会在作用域结束时结束
and and this scope will actually expire, but this variable rather in the scope will obviously end, when the scope ends
但它仍然存在于VertexBuffer中，索引，复制这个，放到这里，我们称它为squareIndices
but it still lives on inside our VertexBuffer, indices, so copy this, put it here, we'll call this squareIndices
我们将创建6个，0 1 2 2 3 0，IndexBuffer将是，我们将创建一个新的，这将和这个一样
we'll make 6 of them, 0 1 2 2 3 0, IndexBuffer is gonna be, we're just gonna make a new one, right, so this is gonna be the same as this
除了IB和IndexBuffer，我们可以继续，我猜，你们也可以像他们说的那样进行重置
except IB and IndexBuffer, we can just go ahead and do make sure I guess, you can also do reset as they said
但那需要2行代码，所以我想我们就这样，调用IndexBuffer::Create()，这将是squareIndices
but that requires 2 lines of code, so I guess we'll just do this, and we do IndexBuffer::Create(), this is going to be our squareIndices
当然那看起来很好，我们可能在另一个括号中有一个，这需要是一个IndexBuffer
of course that looks pretty good, we might have one in another parentheses, this needs to be an IndexBuffer
很好，然后我们将IndexBuffer设置为VertexArray，显然是squareVA，好了，就是那样
okay, cool, and then we just set the IndexBuffer into our VertexArray, obviously being the squareVA, okay, that's it
如果我们向下滚动这里，我们可以看到它是如何运行的
if we scroll down here, we can see how this works
仍然绑定着色器，可以一次绘制两个，可能有点奇怪
so we'll still bind our shader, we can actually draw 2 at once, might be weird
也许要把三角形绘制在正方形的上面，所以先绘制正方形，执行m_SquareVA->Bind()，对吧
maybe we'll draw the triangle on top of the square, so I'll might draw the square first, so we'll say, m_SquareVA->Bind(), right
我们也会绑定m_SquareShader或者m_BlueShader->Bind()，对吧
we'll bind m_SquareShader as well or m_BlueShader->Bind(), right
然后我们会调用glDrawElements，绘制三角形
and then we'll do glDrawElements, we'll draw tart triangles
这将是m_SquareVA, IndexBuffer, GetIndexBuffer->GetCount()，好了
this will be m_SquareVA, IndexBuffer, GetIndexBuffer()->GetCount(), okay
然后我们用VertexArray绑定着色器，然后我们
then we bind the shader with VertexArray, and then we just
三角形，让我们看看会发生什么，希望一切都能顺利
you know do the our triangle, so let's just see what happens here, hopefully everything's gonna work
做的有点仓促，我想有个语法错误，是的，我不知道为什么，但是我的王子们要离开我了
I did kind of rush through this, um okay, we got a syntax error I guess, yep I don't know why, but my princes are just leaving me
那是关于抽象类的一个环节，好吧，我有点想到会发生这种情况
that is about a kind of session in abstract class, yeah okay, I kind of thought that would happen
说实话，这是因为这仍然是一个构造函数，所以我想我们可以直接设置它
to be completely honest, it's because this is still a constructor, so I guess we can either set it directly
如果我们这样做的话，这应该是可行的，尽管我认为可能不是，是的，这变得有点
which should actually work, if we just do that, although I think maybe not, yeah this becomes a little bit
我们最终会返回，我想确保我能运行，但我现在不想处理它
we will eventually return a, I would've thought to make sure I would have worked, but I didn't want to deal with it right now
我只是想这样做，最终我们会返回共享指针，而不是返回原始指针，所以这很好
so I just want to do it this way, eventually we'll return shared pointers, instead of returning raw points, so it'll be fine
但是，我们现在只需要重置，很好，f5，很好，我们有，看起来它仍然在绘制3个顶点
but yeah we'll just do reset for now, okay, cool, f5, all right, cool, so we have, it looks like it's still drawing 3 vertices
但它看起来像在绘制两个东西，用不同的着色器，这很好，为什么它要绘制三个顶点
but it does look like it's drawing 2 things and with different shaders, which is nice, now why is it drawing three vertices
这看起来显然应该多于3，就像我们设置的squareIndices一样，这是6，因为这里有6个
this definitely looks like it should have more than three, like as in we're setting squareIndices, like that's 6, right, because there's 6 in here
然后在这里，我以为我们得到了这个的计数，所以我怀疑我们的IndexBuffer
and then over here, we, I thought we were getting the count out of this, so I'm suspicious now about our IndexBuffer
如果我们看一下Buffer，我们有来自GLIndexBuffer的GetCount, GetCount只返回m_Count
so if we look at Buffer, right, we have GetCount from GLIndexBuffer, GLBuffer, GetCount just returns m_Count
我想我们正在设置它，为什么不呢，m_Count被设置为count，那很奇怪
and I guess we're setting that, right, why wouldn't we be, m_Count is being set to count, that is quite strange
我想知道为什么只绘制了那个，很多快速检查的方法就通过直接调用6来确保真的绘制6个
I wonder why we're only drawing that, many quick way to check is just to make sure that we actually draw 6 by just calling 6 directly
我可能要禁用其他东西，因为这可能不起作用，这可能是我们的布局，实际上是错误的
and I might have to disable the other stuff, because this might not be working, yep okay, cool, so it's probably our layout, that's actually wrong
不幸的是，因为我希望，那只是小菜一碟，但话虽如此，我确实匆匆完成了
unfortunately, because I was hoping that, that would just be a piece of cake, but that being said, I did rush through this
谁知道我写了什么样的代码，这就是问题所在，把IndexBuffer设置为squareVertexArray
so who knows what kind of code I really wrote, and there's the problem, so we have IndexBuffer being set into our squareVertexArray
那实际上就是m_IndexBuffer
that's actually the m_IndexBuffer
也就是IndexBuffer，有3个顶点，确保我们设置了squareIB，对吧
which is the IndexBuffer, which is 3 vertices, so make sure that we set the squareIB, right
然后我们可以往下，把它改成顶点是squareVA->GetIndexBuffer()->GetCount()
and then we can go down, and actually change this back to being vertex was squareVA->GetIndexBuffer()->GetCount()
好了，f5，现在我们可以看到背景中的正方形，以及前景中的三角形
okay, f5 and now we should see both the square in the background, and then the triangle in the foreground
正如你们所看到的，那就是我们得到的结果，它们的大小是一样的
and as you can see, that's what we get here, so they're the same size
那就是为什么你们看到它是这样的
which is why you see it like this
让它更有趣一点，把这个设为0.75而不是0.5，这样我们就有了它作为背景
let's make it a little bit more interesting, and just make this maybe 75 instead of 5, just so that we kind of have it as a background
我们在前面有三角形渲染，稍微小一点，继续，好了，很酷
and we have the triangle rendering in front, and a little bit smaller, there we go, okay, pretty cool
我们现在有了这两个东西，在我们结束之前，我还想做一件事，今天只是清理下代码
we have both of these things now rendering, let's one more thing that I want to do before we finish, today is just clean up the code a bit
你们会注意到，我们实际上不再需要VertexBuffer或IndexBuffer
you'll notice that, we don't actually need to have VertexBuffer or IndexBuffer here anymore
所以我要把这两个都删掉，这样我们就只有这个和那个了
so I'm just gonna delete both of these, right, so we kind of just have this and that
那就意味着，我们要做和这里类似的事情，在这里我们创建了这些东西
that's just going to mean that, we're going to have to do a similar thing to what we did here, where we kind of created this stuff
首先，我们将它命名为VertexBuffer，我想这只是个例子
first, so we'll do, we'll just call this VertexBuffer, so I'll just be kind of out playing example I guess
所以我们要完全替换这个，然后至于这个，我们在这里做同样的操作
so we'll just completely replace this, and then this, we'll do the same thing for here
也就是IndexBuffer，我们叫它IndexBuffer
which will just be IndexBuffer, we'll call it IndexBuffer
我们像往常一样做IndexBuffer->reset()，还有SetBuffer
we'll do IndexBuffer->reset() as usual and SetBuffer
好了，继续，f5，希望这一切都可以
okay, there we go, f5, hopefully this all works
实际上这里有一些错误，让我们看看，哦，是的，我们在这里使用它
and we actually have some errors here, let's see, and oh yeah we use it here
很明显这就变成了m_VertexArray->GetIndexBuffer()->GetCount()，我想应该就是那样
so this so obviously now just becomes m_VertexArray->GetIndexBuffer()->GetCount(), and I think that should be it
看看得到了什么，你们可以看到，它在运行，很好，我要做的最后一件事是清理这个
so let's just see what we get here, you can see, it's working, which is great, last thing I'll do to clean this up as well is
我们需要删除VertexArray，我没有添加析构函数，因为这里只有这个东西
we need to actually delete our VertexArray, so I didn't add a destructor, because I just had this thing here
那么我们就复制这个到构造函数下面，使它成为一个函数
so we will just copy this go below the constructor, make this a function
只需要调用glDeleteVertexArrays，好了，然后就是m_RendererID
and just call glDeleteVertexArrays, okay, and this will be one, and m_Vertex, m_RendererID, and RendererID
好了，酷，只要确保一切正常，我想就差不多了
okay, cool, just make sure that everything still works, and I think that's pretty much it
希望这能帮助你们理解VertexArray是如何运行的，以及我们将如何使用它们
so hopefully this kind of helps you guys understand how VertexArray work, and how we're gonna use them
现在我们已经有了足够多的代码，我们可以不用写OpenGL代码来实现这些东西
and now we kind of have almost almost enough code, where we can actually not write OpenGL code to make any of this stuff happen
我们可以把这个移到Sandbox到SandboxApp
and we can actually move this into Sandbox into the SandboxApp
而不是把它放在Application中，最后一部分实际上就是这个glDrawElements
instead of actually having it inside Application, the last piece of the puzzle is literally this glDrawElements
我们将在下期讨论这个问题，好了，所以我希望你们喜欢这期视频
and we're going to talk about that in the next episode, okay, so I hope you guys enjoyed this episode
如果喜欢的话，就为它点赞吧，也可以通过访问patreon.com/thecherno来支持这个系列
if you did, you can hit the like button, you can also have support the series by going over the patreon.com/thecherno
非常感谢所有支持这个系列的粉丝，如果你们支持这个系列，就会得到奖励
huge thank you as always to all the patreons that make this series possible, if you support the series, you'll get rewarded by just
你们会得到一定的奖励，比如可以访问我的Hazel私人开发库的源代码
you get certain rewards, such as getting access to the source code of my kind of private development repository of Hazel
我们就得到了类似于PBR的渲染，就像一个完整的3个场景和很多非常酷的东西
where we've got like PBR rendering, and just like a full 3 scene and a lot of really cool stuff
这里还在开发中，下期，我说过，我想谈谈渲染器，以及它是如何发挥作用的
there's kind of in development there, next time as I said, I want to talk about the renderer, and how that plays the role
以及绘制元素，因为那是我们实际的比如draw命令，那是我们实际的DrawCall
and where that chill draw elements is going, because that's our actual like draw command, that's our actual DrawCall
是的，我们会继续搞这个，可能会开始构建，把一个真正漂亮的场景组合在一起
and yeah, we'll kind of move on with this, and probably start kind of building, putting together like an actual pretty scene
再见，那么，拜
I'll see you guys, then goodbye